go ahead and get your file for today's
fecha fifteen
and
open up rather set up
for that work for oil and the
datafile that create for crossover don't
uncompressed that file
you can if you really want to
but all my instructions were really the
compressed into slow today to write a
compressed file
do you what that means that there might
be too imax
windows open
and you may treat the other one
it doesn't look like that's the case and
we do a controlled ki
he's free to go back to the child's used
in the actual for suffer
and i don't get reread offers the desk
so as possible
press enter
yes collapses
it's been lately his reasoning
yes that's a good fit problem here
finally
c handful even from your startup
you probably
uh...
surfcontrol t
now save it and in the work of operating
and all the alexander
if you want to call after that
shipped out
clocks
so today
it's time to stop being boring with just
tax burger plot stuff today
stuff you guys are ready
i try to make it easier so that
uh... you don't have to worry about
right now what we did last time
when you download this
the zip file
that's right here
that file
is got the data that's been parsed
taking it from that really crazy
nema format and turn into something a
lot simpler
so we're going to work through that
what they had people look at what our
g_p_s_ is doing on earth
and decide whether i think the g_p_s_ is
doing a good job
hopefully you've got
uh... directory like this week
you are bio if you want it there
and
the visa to file
we don't need to
uncompressed it because the two
attorneys and python so they can
actually read
the zip compressed files
there is the amount that is that if you
have a time of text data they can get
very big quickly
anyone whose log to pass a multi being
the events in the text format
will know that it likes to philip brutus
too fast as possible so maybe a
compressed is a good thing
so we can do
uh... bc acts
and then in our file
and like that to happen with the done
many times at this point
and we can see the first lines of our
data file
and i'm hoping is that looks to you guys
a lot friendlier then that format we had
last time
so we should see
first-line that's a comments line with a
pound beginning
and then
i've put in
that column names so that we can
remember them without having to
magically know what they are
so we've got in here
longitude
and a lot of skin
now be warned high tend to do things can
x_y_z_
and a lot of people will do
why at city which to me seems very
strange
because that's not arrayed in a corner
frame
so i try to stick with the right
according frame x_y_z_
and stay away from flat
lat long interview long live
if you see me going backwards instru
dept
set out because
so there's no dissent for today
and we can also do a quick
wordcount see how much data we have
we have
eighty six thousand
points i'd like it everything all and
double check and make sure they're good
points
admitted when grappling is important
because we never had a look at all those
points there's no
there's no way
so let's go ahead and start up
fight on
typewriters are shell with pi lab
and if you forget by eleven
it's gonna be really unfunded a because
we are definitely
doing lots of
slowly started i'd played on
were going to work with
of very command called
loaded tfc this is a part of a package
called number line
brought in by pi lab
and load taxed
is
i'm very neat tool that knows how to
read in alarms number are
formats
we enter here
and get some help
it'll give us some description
emphatically
assume everything is a floating point
number of which
should work for us okay today
it knows that if a wind starts with that
found that the comment that's pretty
cool for us
to a mature nine it'll say down below
that if we don't tell anyone that are
it seems that center of white space
between each of our columns
how we could also talent explicitly we
wanna comically did the here we just
have white-space
ross of entrapment this unpack
featured down here so we can take a look
through those
really give it up by a lame
and if we notice in the description here
it says if the file an extension is
going to easy or dot be easy to
it no list
to first uncompressed that file on the
flying
so that's our
he needs a ticket to keep the compressed
or not there were about to die
and we're going to come back and look at
unpack and then to be able to pull apart
the data
if you are
data is nicely format as attached file
load tax is a great way
he did it in so that you can work with
it
so if you didn't fight
which is on the screen
low-tax will not appear to have a pilot
yep i didn't put in our class notes here
for him because i figured if somebody
differently
not remember the q
from the back from tijuana ron
uh... high python dash dash highlight
in your case they are keeping a low tax
question marks who happens
so now
let's go ahead and try out
the sample of lawyer david we have here
sold to data
equals and if you don't do the equal
sign is going to dump a giant amount
in fact eighty six thousand lines of
text on your screen you don't really
want
solo t exceeds recall the function
remember that we can use tabs to
complete file names
so ill completely out
a memo and the privacy on the right
and if you hit enter
it should take left for the second floor
data and
and you can then type
and print the seas and data
and it will tell us what it did
this is a special day tight there's a
whole i recall the numbed by design four
high-performance numerical analysis
we can run for a transforms on the stock
for all kinds of really cool features
and is designed to be
compact in fast
all you need to know is that it's
convenient networks
so if we typed
justia to see what happens to see what's
in there
the nice thing about this is the nearby
python it's not gonna
it gives you a nice and i like this it
will actually trying to get you out
fairly friendly version of it
and what we've got here
arrays
that represents
it's basically a list of a arrays aneesh
one of those entries and there is going
to be one of our records
so let's go ahead and idea of sub-zero
and get one the back and see what it
looks like
and what would get back is
we look at our columns so we have x_y_z_
quality satellites and h dot as your
report on world lucien of persuasion
which if you haven't taken a class about
but you will see them
that comes back and one record
unfortunate we really wants
all of our taxes and one bigger rates
will comply accidents why things like
that
so this isn't really a convenient form
for us to have the data
is really kind of
wausau kind it is very annoying
so over into is used that unpack feature
to pull apart day types that are in
there
and the way we do that
is we give it a name for each of the
fields so we've got
if we say
uh... at one of those records we have
six different fields that we've got to
give names to you
and they're going to come in the order
of our columns
sewers a calm
acts
orion z
and then we get
quality
satellites
do you know p
loads the ecstasy
and ignoring the notes we have the and
pete dot that's not break right now
this is what we had before
so it's not over for adam anu option and
their certainly a comma
and we're gonna say unpack
equals troops as tells it to go off
pull apart each of those
columns from our data and fill 'em out
has problems as opposed to getting into
this rose
bc i have an extra people find that
they're cdbaby equals dole load text
you have just overwritten below text
fortune you've resigned low-tech fifty
that string
so i would suggest that you quit attbi
point on
and restart i fight on
because you've wiped out
in python you can assign anything to a
function
and he will then replace that function
so you've lost will text in that
so go ahead and quit out of our
part-time restarted
so go ahead and hit enter with this
and hopefully
works for all of you
doing allies
so you've got it there so do
in the notes i have an extra and p dot
but that's a typo
i'll need it
i think that's
meant to come in later in the class so
go back up and remove the and peed on
because that's incorrect
and then it should work gets done about
that
then the charges that you just have
reached house
yet this happens this is my tries to
look around the lives of canada and
probably working with the file name
someone to give you the filing press
office and
matches
now we have our delivery as
nice separate variables we can take up
peek at what they look like
go ahead and tight
acts in to see what happens
and what we have here is an array of for
longitude
we've got all of our launch he's coming
back from the g_p_s_ in series
within the same with wine
you'll see
are latitudes
there's some really nice functions built
and we can say
aborigine can
a team in town
and then he said acts
disconnect average everything in an
array in the back
the average
value for the position for the archie
p_s_
prepared for this one because we know
the g_p_s_ isn't moving unless someone
is dragging her building away
itself it's just that they're on the
roof
our best estimate is taking all but they
didn't have urging it is our best
estimate the location of our g_p_s_
you can do the same for wine
he fought those two up on a map you
should
foothold
mark breakdown pop barbell
they could also be fun things like you
can say noon
of acts
and get a minimum back
if you forget women as you can always do
you a question mark on it helps a little
bit about it
might be a little confusing to some of
you
if you do you
percent who you can't say to leave
anyone the variables that you want to
get rid of
you're always welcome to do that
but they're right now there's no reason
to believe anything that we've got to be
made
year old data
only a few on belief that you're welcome
to do it
how do you know it kept
them all in the right
orders and i wish that disk does for
registered with the uh... kentucky acts
incident coming in order
you could also take a couple numbers and
to compete
if you'd you'd like to have you can take
a look at the first couple of theater
coming out right
let's just get a plot up
of our expel you
this is going to give us our first
peaking too
how would you guess is doing
so this is the plot of
the longitude of our g_p_s_
now i'll expect you to know exactly how
the any
thousandth of a lot
wanted to greens here right
outstanding is completely useless number
for us
so we're going out in a bit look at how
i convert that
the motion of the x and y into a meters
from our average
but this gives you a general sense that
it's pretty stable you know compared to
you something from the nineteen fifties
if you're doing a satellite picks in the
early sixties from
when the first
fatten that system that would be moving
quite a bit more
so so it's probably pretty good you can
plot
the wire variable
so that's going to be are a lot of
seeing
we have something that we don't want
it's trying to plot both the acts in the
wise to separate one for the same graph
which means that
the variation into those is
pretty much probably want
bears a couple ways you can do without
the first one
as you can always say c l_ a_ n_
which cleared out your graph
and i don't actually know what c l_ a_
stands for
tacit clear the current axes
and then you can reply
just by itself
and then if you want to go back to
exceed three plot
nuclear unemployed acts
it's basically sort of interactive and
elite figured out
active vs
delays in private
breed upon that
so i'm showing you
i try to teach you guys the way i wish i
had been taught to plot
because i want the plot with the new
plot allies friends
fifteen years of canoe plot and writes
me insane
it's not very flexible
it's really grumpy
and it doesn't like to do things like
poor plots and there's nothing to do
very well
map pollard is way more powerful but
that means i also don't know what as
well as i hope in the plot
so i'm still trying to act
figure out all melissa
at holland
but the nice thing is we didn't
tell it to switch between figures
did a good thing to go with this is
anything you or what this if you go over
to matlab
applauding in matlab
uh... this is trying to mimic
how matt my brother's plodding
clotting in matlab is really awesome
and so they copied
what they thought was a great design
it's works really well by phone
they're keeping we can do is we can say
figure to you could have a number of
numbered figures
and it's gonna pull up
on the screen a second window
that i have no space to really put
somewhere
you can switch back and forth between
easily can plot
x
in
this figure to and why in figure one
so then you can start if you've got a
screen is big enough to see what's going
on you can start plotting up all over
different graphs and look at the next to
each other
but really what we wanted to you is
probably more like something like this
will do a c l_ a_ to clear
and really
want to be doing plot x comma y
so if this is going to use plot
the excel use against the white values
franklin plotting
are latching onto separately
we get caning what test
so this is our g_p_s_
the position of it over an entire day
if that's not too many years and that's
probably a pretty good thing that you
can see that it's pretty random is
it's uh...
senator i'm area without
any via fax one way or the other we have
one mls bike sticking out the top
in general
it's a very nice type old stuff it's not
paying off to too far
and we'll have to later on cm years that
is
misses a lot better plot bernard katz
and why separately but sometimes you
just wanna plot took the part of that
uh... tickets once a second
from eighty six thousand yet so i want
to second
i don't know if it's tightly controlled
to one second purposes going as fast as
they can
that's great
but when you start having local figures
it's kind of important to be able to
label things and if you want to print
them out
and do something your notebook you don't
have labels on things it's going to get
that fast
so let's go or how to put some labels on
the first thing we can use that i don't
speedy trial prep the season in the
string inside that you want
and will call a g_p_s_ warner
one day
if you were actually doing this for your
notebook
i want for your the date that this was
for a few more
you more things on here
so you actually figure out which they
have a real funny
bioflavonoids and why i think it's
so we can say x label
james warren g_
the
and plessy wanted appears
right up here
we can say that while able
by the two
quality of aroma left's and works pretty
well
before i go any further let me give you
a sense of how powerful this is and how
little i know of map pollen
you can go way beyond my skills
really cover the top
there's uh... gallery
on that follows
website
and when you're boring you wanna see
pretty pictures
and you feel like grass
here's some of the sample graphic they
were able to see their even able to draw
part
they've got polar plots
they've got
from old triangle taping they've got
through some sort of system
these are all graphs made with map plot
led and they give you the sample script
on how to make each one of those
if u
thank you for your biologist both i'd
like to do with your plot to kill a
whisker plots
uh... you can do
things that are to be images
you could do all kinds of stuff
draw crazy pictures
departure arts
and there's a picture of a
person
you can do all kinds of crazy stuff with
it so that's cool
the more you are with the demo reel be
able to pull off some of these pool
graphs that
i don't get no idea myself
you can turn
into s fijian skill doctor graphics that
that working illustrator you can make
images of p_n_g_ zinc it's things like
that
it's pretty flexible in terms of what it
while quit
so if you're trying to make a figure
career poster
this is a great tool for being able to
uh...
recreate simple graphics
so let's do a little bit more to make
this
more useful we can add once you've got a
plot up you can add other plots on top
of it
let's floppy average
of the accent why so so the center
points that this uh... is
wandering around so we can say plots
and we can say coverage
acts
com ar have a rich
wine
and then i had some special
text rings
however a couple more pop my head
but we can say oh or
inside therefore red
and hope for circle
so the default is
i start off with a blue line
to connect all the points
if we just wanted to a red circle
we now have a little tiny red circle
medal at the center point
uh... pat
massive twelve points
and we can do something like we could
throw label on it computer labels that
ticker locations
so you can say
indicates
center tereko center text there let me
say it's gonna be a x_y_ of
coverage acts
how much have a rich
wine
and uh... getting it done a great number
of pregnancies and sometimes hard
so there need to be three practices on
the right time this one came back down
side
there's nothing right there at the
moment
so if it hasn't drawn that particular
part of the graph you can save show
and it will try to draw everything
and frank
that's right you there dallas center
that's part of projector you really
can't see
but on your screen you can hopefully see
a little black center written on there
if you look at the new notes it's got
all kinds of things we can change the
font you can make it bold
it's which the color
critical you can actually see
here
if we want to go to figure two
we're now on figure to use overall now
other one that's back here
it's got a lot of state so we're gonna
see some work that we're gonna build
some subplots worry to one figure with
local plots together
you have to remember
which partner on sees how it'll pay now
i'm working on the subplot lovely way to
ask it
but typically that's kind of confusing
and hard to find so
he's long as you keep telling it where
you're at then you're good
so let's get dainty now and let's do
some actual geospatial work
so we're gonna go ahead and try to you
you know why recalled proj pure o_j_
that was a reason britain at the u_s_
g_s_
in uh... leave the seventies
and insert often for training that was
kinda scary
but it's been improved over the years
and turned into a really amazing
projection library so it knows all about
ellipsoids projections
and he transformed a tiff between all
sorts of different core difference for
you
bring it back
it actually knows about distances on the
ellipsoids
and so we can talk to a great circle
distance between two points so that you
don't have to do it
there's updates fairly often as people
add new projections
and it's god
several
like baby and twenty thousand
projections and
turkey is that controls the issue
bailout nightline
so let's give
project right
and we'll see if we can project some
data
subjected to at least get ourselves out
assistance
soldiers were giving useful ever called
by proj
that's a wrapper around some c code
so important
by proj
you need to really know what's in there
and then it works
you have to create object that knows
which ellipsoids working with
so we're say
g_e_ odi and i don't really know what it
that stands for
and we're going to try proj module
and leave their g_o_t_
and in fact before eating that
were asking for help
and you can see
that is not terribly helpful
the piper i start
geology owed
with a capital g
presenter
and we'll tell you a little bit about
forwarded inverse geodetic refereed
circle computations
an area did you not enough information
to really figure out what's good
all guide you through the actual process
of
setting up so
so if you see right
so here i was just typing time
it gave me the simplest uh... three
things are possible
and i had to finish it out
yet that was me
income
so if you noticed on the screen if there
is a thirty four dash two thirty four
again
didn't i didn't answer
so you try to run the command that
wasn't going to work
that's not yet so
i'm working on the command thirty-five
so start with thirty five
my thirty five
so i know there's a good keep your can
you guys up for the rest of semester but
katie he stopped myself at this point i
hit tab all the time
and so
you're gonna see partial completion to
come along to you gotta keep an eye on
figures number thirty four
and here's again thirty four that means
i haven't hit enter
you're looking at a partial coming and
that if you press the enter
after typing in
the facts
you're gonna get some sort of strange
air
uh... probably say i don't know what
heights
so i apologize for it
because you can't make it
hopefully do you guys will start
catching them
more often
if he had figured why do you guys enough
time to write you know you'll figure it
out at home
so let's get this thing settled and we
just thought which ellipsoid
curtly don't over how to ask if
ellipsoids
tulips equals
though the u_s_ eighty-four so if you
know anything about ellipsoids
this is the one that's used for g_p_s_
systems
your hope we can all learn alzheimer
about
geography
but you're not going for me
soaring to more of the mechanics and
only would be ritu probably some up
who will be talking to you about
ellipsoids angie are seeing a lot
here were disconnect
get it done continued to go after the
details of the matter
sofa run back to me and
that's going to give us this
g_ o_ d_ who do you know i don't know
how to say this
objects
put a period after a few hit tab to find
out what is going to billable
but that sonya four ignore open
governor's scores a goal of over on the
right
and has to things in here that we care
about forward
an inverse
whether you're going from
uh... points
and a distance and direction or if
you're going from two points
and you want to figure out the distance
and direction between the two
we're gonna use
the inverse which takes two points
and give it back
direction and distance between those two
points
those given a shot
school say inverse
we can pick two points so i'm gonna take
acts
morning
y_-one
and i'm gonna do
take a gamble
i'm anti-tax minus one
and why minus one thought the very last
point
if you guys remember delays that we've
done
minus one is the very last one
slash this isn't the first one that
would be thrilled onto the actual
firstborn
zero was the first ones will be first in
last
this is debbie the distance
and direction between the first point
was taken during that day and a lot
point
solar hit enter cross our fingers
what you're going to get back
rapid ask it
question mark on the
inverse call
and it's going to tell us hopefully
returns before and back as most which is
the direction
india grease
and then the distance so we have
this is going to be the direction from
the first point uh... watch points
this is the opulent direction from the
last point to the first point
and then this is how far apart they are
and i believe it's in meters doesn't
actually tell us that you know it's a
newspaper yes distances are in years
in one day this g_p_s_ has drifted five
point two meters from that starting
point to the ending point
which doesn't seem too bad in the stock
great but
doesn't mean that agrees
no
that's just during those points and it
might have wonder back closer so there's
probably uh... distance that this was
greater than that
solely at least nobody able to calculate
the distance and we know our g_p_s_ is
rightfully ok if we
if that distance of five years isn't too
terrible for us
if you're trying to do
before one of the party k the real fun
imax g_p_s_ for surveying you want some
centimeter
with the fact we have a problem
so meeting quite uses g_p_s_ for fixing
stuff like that
so let's go ahead and try to use this
to create a function rekindle cross all
of our data
and calculate the distance from the
appalachian and the direction from the
average
for every single point
for our data set
business is good
be going back to wearing at a rate
functions and creating something they
can actually handle
i do that
so let's go ahead and create something
mccall wonder
dot pines
for calculating longer
so we're gonna need are pipe raj library
against wind import that into this final
import higher price that we can do that
that you know it
in berkeley need to create a function
wanderlust
so it's going to create a list
the wonders
deviate from our average points
so this is creating a function if you
remember
says i want to create function
and then
here we're doing it by the name of our
function so wonder lists
to parentheses will be our arguments
what we're gonna pass then reynolds
wrapping up again
cohen says we're going to go ahead and
start it
inside there
we can certainly do that we do
we don't have to have it here its
i can do it just because it's great
because then you can right from the back
shell later on to
is not required
it's tends to be a good thing to do so
i'll go ahead and do it
if we didn't do it we'll be ok for now
might later on find out that we had some
trouble
so let's go ahead and start working on
this functions we need to bring back in
but we did with it you know
adornment announces some hope that some
way
so history misti we've been doing
so here is our import that we didn't
the reader create one of these are
different use it in the transformations
edit copy
it's the same here
then grew more load in all of that data
that we did before
way back here for me this is number
seven
we were in that area
at copley
paste that into limo the day inside of
our function
now this is an agreat function because
typically run one right functions you
can reuse later on
and having a hard coded by elaine just
kind of bad
but we're going to be lazy finale felt
works
because
worrying about too many things at once
will contact you not
okay so now we want to have our average
is that we can use as we went through
all the points source computer are
averages
so x
equals
cabarets
uh... acts
and why i have equals average of y
now i'm doing this
once at the beginning rather than each
somewhere in the loop we could kapiti
average on-the-fly
but that's an expensive thing to do
because to calculate the average it has
to read the entire right
and then runs a map on that computer
number
so we want to have things like averages
particularly if you can
and there's going to be a a big problem
here
if we eat
you over here and we say
average
dysfunction came in with our pile up
well i think that that espy lab is
pretty cool
hides things
and typically opine python programmers
always like to be explicit saying where
the models come from
which for the code
gives you a particular function
and doing these
massive imports were you just take
entire project and pull in tears
uh... working space
museo have no idea where average came
from
and and i have to tell you the average
comes from something called num five so
we've got to go get numb by it
and find average
if things like plotkin average on our
part of the normal python shell so we
have to bring them back into one
so we'll have to do
imports
non-buying
if we use something a lot
make an alias for two comes into the
different name
because it has
and pete
normally i wouldn't trade heat you guys
something like this but everybody does
it
so if you read someone else's
co-dependency
and p dot all over in vertices stuck in
my notes accidentally
happen or show you that import ads
so what you can do here here is the
creating a new name for it so we could
say in four prior prior to something
else to we wanted
we could say
annoying name
and we could then refer to it as some
really annoying name
but i don't want to do that
this is one everybody seems to do so
we're just gonna stick with it
so we don't need to say
and p dot
coverage
and p dot average if you want to see
that was right over here and uh...
i fight on terminal
will say imports
here in implied as
and he
and then you can see emptied period
and then the tab ki and you'll see all
the things that come in
umpire
so it's got lots of
fun stuff in there
that you can going through a cure
leisure
site it actually has
average
i apologize is a little more confusing
than i would like to be but i'm trying
to follow the content of the people tend
to use
so their function now
it should hopefully
compute the average x and y
so why would go ahead and try it save
print x
and then remember to save
so control x control s
there should be no stars down here at
the bottom
so could you tell us
will see that we have a wanted up high
in there
and i cross my fingers will seem run
wonder
an agreement
hope it works hit enter
gets what he did nothing
so you have no idea why
bring the scripts
printed absolutely nothing
and why didn't the load anything
friend blvd
exact really never called the function
let's not run it
will do in civil duty import
wonder
like we did last time and then we'll say
a period
lah tab
and bullsandbears actually wanderlust
down here
wanderlust
and to put his or her run that function
with inside of our wander model
presenter
and we're gonna find our first set of
bugs that we didn't know about
rotex
also comes from num buying and i missed
and p dot there
hopefully
i don't miss any more of them
so now
if we did
import
it's not gonna work so import only works
the first time and then it's
kind words cashed
it's bloated and and they operate system
tries to beat
careful about keeping around for doesn't
try to work harder than it has to do
this
and run it
is exactly same bug we have to do a
reload
so there was reloaded
and now if we go back up and money
gave me her average are exxon our lives
remember when you guys
type of stuff and python karen berry
much about your indentation
so if you're deaf
for function is not on the left hand
side of the spring
you're going to have problems
so if you have any extra spaces in here
like say something like that
it's not going to work see one of the
all the way up against the left-hand
column
and remember to use the tab he too
intense
sify pressed happen here
give invasion scared looks old walkie
econnect cabinet will take you right
back to the right indentation
let me max do the work for you for
indentation
it's not going to try and count
spaces
and he imported singaporean saying he
will load
yet once you've important you have to do
a remote from downtown
are you gonna call the function so you
have parentheses after
yet so
you can also put the cursor analysis is
actually english words of click on that
he could do price pal
method dollar
and see how it saying at this point
misspelled
so prices here are hoping it will give
you everything
surprise zero speedy yet
guessed by now
note so that even though the modules
united steel wanted on one who knows
us he had a phone sex with different
he'd had this file name in him
co had
i had been working there for a final
and so i have a wall follow
seem to change that to be myself
socio it's got to do you think that that
that means that you would
we don't have anything because
the without the parentheses you're just
actually referencing the functions the
election call parentheses hopeful
uh... yet is it so well uses friends
about when you are ron one that's what
this means
i think a lot of missus
people watching and every time we do it
just repeat yourself which one of the
human body
and hopefully it's terrific
here i will start picking up those
things happen
and on tuesday we're going to keep going
through this
i wold do this all up in the video so if
you want to watch that video before the
next class that'll be great then we can
go through it and make sure everybody's
up to speed on plotting
you get here for all of your data so
can't be able to plot is super important
general research
for trying to all he really comfortable
with it